In the first half of the 20th century,
台 灣 人 民 在 二 十 世 紀 前 半 期
the people of Taiwan underwent modernization
經 歷 日 本 的 殖 民 統 治
under Japan's colonial rule.
開 始 了 現 代 化 的 歷 程
But with the empire going into war,
但 是 隨 著 日 本 帝 國 的 參 戰
Taiwanese people also experienced miseries
台 灣 人 也 經 歷 了 苺 難 的 生 活
and devastations from wars.
與 戰 火 的 蹂躪
They prayed for the war to end
他 們 期 筌 戰 爭 早 日 結 束
but were uncertain and worried
但 是 對 於 戰 爭 結 束 後 的 命 運
about the future it may bring.
範 遼 感 到 徬 徨 與 不 3 與 不 安
At the end of World War II,
第 二 次 世 界 大 戰 末 期
the U.S. bombarded Taiwan's
美 國 一 方 面 用 B29 轟 炸 機
military and industrial bases with B-29s
轟 炸 台 灣 本 島 的 軍 事 ， 工 業 區
and dropped handbills to call people
一 方 面 又 投 下 傳 單
to revolt against Japanese rule.
號 召 台 澧 灣 人 反 抗 日 本 統 治
Over 100,000 of these handbills were distributed.
這 樣 的 傳 單 有 十 萬 張 以 上
Sir...
老 師 …
Wars cause the destruction of public facilities,
戰 爭 會 帶 來 公 共 設 施 的 破 破 壞
shortage of food and the spread of diseases.
糧 食 缺 乏 ， 疾 病 流 行 等 苺 惱
The best way
為 防 止 這 些 菩 惱 持 續 擴 大
to prevent the problems from worsening
最 好 的 方 法
is to stop the war.
即 是 要 軍 閨 停 止 戰 爭
China and the U.S. cooperated
太 平 洋 中 美 兩 大 國
in the Pacific to defeat the Japanese
聯 合 決 心 掃 蕩 日 寇
for Taiwan's freedom.
恢復 台 灣 人 民 的 自 由
On August 6th and 9th of 1945,
1945 年 8 月 6 日 和 9 日
the U.S. dropped two atomic bombs
美 國 的 兩 穎 原 子 彈
on Hiroshima and Nagasaki, respectively.
分 別 在 日 本 的 廣 島 與 長 崎 引 爆
Six days later,
六 天 之 後
on the 15th of August,
8 月 15 日
Emperor Showa's surrender speech
日 本 昭 和 天 皇 透 過 無 線 電
was broadcasted over the radio
向 全 日 本 的 軍 人 及 百 姓
to the people of Japan,
親 自 廣 播 投 降 詛 書
which marked the end of the war.
二 汀 大 戰 終 於 結 束
After 50 years of
歷 經 日 本 殖 民 統 治
colonial rule under Japan,
五 十 年 的 台 灣 人 民
the people of Taiwan was about to face a new era.
即 將 面 對 一 個 新 的 時 代
I unconditionally accept the Potsdam Declaration.
熟 條 件 接 受 波 茨 坦 宣 言
It hurts me to see my people suffer,
不 忍 國 民 更 受 以 上 的 犧 牲
so I endure the unendurable.
所 以 思 所 難 忍
You have to wait for the right time.
﹣ 苔 k 等 ﹣ 需 炳 ﹒ 錘 勝 芝 ﹣ 巹 ﹣ ﹒ 嚐 ﹒
Do not act rashly.
不 可 輕 舉 姑 動
We won...
贏 啡 …
We won.
嬴 啡
After Japan's surrender,
日 本 投 降 後
all the Japanese in Taiwan, were deported back home.
在 台 灣 的 日 本 人
Only the technicians
除 了 技 術 人 員 可 暫 時 留 在 台 灣
could stay temporarily.
其 他 一 律 強 行 遣 送 回 國
Among them,
其 中 日 本 軍 人
36,600 were soldiers
共 三 萬 六 千 六 百 人
and approximately 500,000 were civilians.
加 上 日 僑 約 五 十 萬 人
All personal properties were confiscated.
私 人 財 產 一 律 沒 收
Each person was only allowed
毐 人 行 李 限 定
to carry three pieces of luggage.
只 能 攜 帶 三 個 柳 條 箱
The first ship left on December 25, 1945.
從 1945 年 12 月 25 日
The deportation didn't end
第 一 艘 船 離 開 起
until April of the next year.
到 1946 年 4 月 才 告 一 段 落
Japan was defeated
日 本 戰 敗
and Taiwan was returned to China.
台 灣 重 回 中 國 統 治
The people of Taiwan
台 灣 人 的 身 分
were no longer Japanese but Chinese again.
又 從 日 本 人 變 成 中 國 人
According to our position
我 們 地 方 的 立 場
I officially declare the establishment of
我 們 宣 布 三 民 主 義 青 年 團
the Three Principals of the People Youth League.
在 今 天 正 式 成 立
Self-motivated community leaders
此 時 台 灣 各 地 的
and young intellects
許 多 地 方 領 袖 和 知 識 青 年
formed local youth leagues
自 動 自 發
and vigilante groups
在 地 方 上 組 纓 青 年 團 體
all across Taiwan
或 治 安 # 維 持 會
to uphold public order and security
在 各 街 庄 擔 負 起
by patrolling the streets.
維 持 地 方 治 安 與 秩 序 的 貧 任
Public properties were thus
使 得 大 量 的 公 有 物 資
saved from theft and destruction.
沒 有 被 偷 竊 或 者 損 壤
Water and electricity were provided as usual,
﹒ 皆 進 水 電 照 常 供 給
and railroad transportation was smooth.
鐵 路 交 通 也 可 以 暢 通 無 阻
This one is good.
這 幅 好
Let me see.
我 幫 你 看 看
Local groups welcomed the
民 間 團 體
establishment of a KMT organizing committee
歡 迎 國 民 政 府 籌 備 會 的 成 立
and exercise some political influence.
也 發 揮 了 一 些 政 治 作 用
This group was started by Chen Hsin,
這 個 團 體 是 由 日 治 時 期
the pioneer of Taiwanese banking.
台 灣 的 本 土 金 融 業 先 驅
Since the Japanese occupation.
陳 炘 所 發 起
It brought together national movement activists
結 合 了 林 獻 堂 ， 葉 榮 鐘 等
such as Lin Hsien-Tang and Yeh Jung-Chung.
民 族 運 動 人 士 組 織 而 成
In addition to welcoming the fatherland,
籌 備 會 除 了 帶 頭 營 造
the preparatory committee is also committed to
歡 迎 祖 國 的 新 氣 象 外
maintaining peace and order.
也 致 力 於 維 持 治 安 和 秩 序
Taiwan was able to come through
在 兩 個 政 權 轉 移 的
the confusion during the 50 days
五 十 天 混 亂 期
of the regime transfer,
台 灣 能 夠 平 安 度 遇
due to the effort of
這 些 知 識 青 年
these young intellectuals
與 民 間 領 袖 的 努 力
and community leaders.
發 揮 了 一 定 的 安 撫 效 果
In "Golden Dewdrop,"
作 家 吳 漕 流 在 ﹁ 台 灣 連 翹 」 中
writer Wu Cho-Liu described
描 速 了 這 段
how the people in Taiwan feel when waiting for
等 待 ﹁ 被 國 」 接 收 時 期
"the fatherland” to take over.
台 灣 人 民 的 心 情
Shih. (Chinese phonic symbol)
7 刊
Chi.
圖 語
Six million people began to study
六 百 萬 人 以 燃 燒 一 般 的 氣 夥
Mandarin Chinese with fervor.
開 始 學 習 中 國 語 和 中 文
Those who knew how to speak it
懂 得 中 國 語 和 中 文 的 人
offered their services
主 動 地
as voluntary teachers
當 中 國 語 講 習 所 的 義 務 講 師
at Chinese study centers.
無 酬 給 民 眾 教 授 語 言
People wanted to make Taiwan
人 人 希 望 把 台 灣 建 設 成
a better place than it was under Japan's rule.
比 日 本 時 代 更 美 好 的 地 方
Please have some water.
請 喝 水
Is that correct?
我 這 樣 講 標 準 嗎
Not bad.
不 錯
On October 17th,
10 月 17 日
Chinese troops entered Taipei from Keelung
中 國 軍 隊 搭 乘 接 收 的 日 艦
aboard an expropriated Japanese vessel
由 美 軍 第 七 艦 隊 護 送
escorted by the U.S. Seventh Fleet.
從 基 隆 登 陸 進 入 台 北 市
Taiwanese people welcomed
台 灣 人 民 以 瘋 狂 似 的 熟 情
these officials and troops from the fatherland
迎 接 他 們 心 目 中 的
with a frenzied passion.
祠 國 官 員 和 軍 隊
Crowds gathered in the Keelung Harbor.
基 隆 碼 頭
And the streets of Taipei.
台 北 市 街 都 出 現 擁 擠 的 人 潮
As the troops disembarked,
可 是 祖 國 的 軍 隊 一 上 岸 後
people realized it was not like
台 灣 民 眾 發 現
what they had imagined.
和 自 己 想 像 的 並 不 太 一 樣
On October 25, 1945, a Japanese representative
34 年 10 月 25 號
signed to surrender at Zhongshan Hall in Taipei.
日 本 代 表
Taiwan and Penghu were returned.
在 台 北 中 山 堂 簽 字 投 降
After 50 years in enemy's hands,
淪 陷 五 十 年 的 台 灣
Taiwan has finally returned to the fatherland.
重 回 祖 國 懷 拖
Fellow Taiwanese countrymen
萬 生 的 台 灣 同 胞
have regained their freedom
再 見 天 日
and given a new life.
重 獲 自 由
On October 25,
10 月 25 日
the ceremony of accepting Japan's surrender
中 國 戰 區 台 灣 省 受 降 典 禮
was held at the Taipei City Hall.
在 台 北 市 公 會 堂 舉 行
The representative from Taiwan and Penghu
台 澎 地 區 的 意 降 代 表
was Chief Executive Chen Yi.
由 台 灣 省 行 政 長 官 陳 儀 擔 任
The surrender was signed by
日 方 代 表 則 由
ex-Governor-General Ando Rikichi.
原 台 灣 總 督 安 藤 利 吉 簽 署 降 書
Mr. Lin Mosei
林 茂 生 先 生 在 當 日 公 會 堂 中
was Taiwan's representative.
擔 任 台 灣 省 人 民 代 表
Lin was the first doctor of philosophy in Taiwan.
他 是 台 灣 第 一 位 晦 學 博 士
He was claimed missing in the 228 Incident.
後 來 不 幸 於 二 二 八 事 件 中 失 蹤
His son, Lin Tsung-Yi, said
他 的 兒 子 林 宗 義
at an interview on the 228 Incident...
在 二 二 八 口 迷 歷 史 訪 談 中 說
On October 25th of that year,
那 年 10 月 25 日
Taiwan celebrated its first Retrocession Day.
咽 台 灣 歡 度 第 一 個 台 灣 光 復 節
That evening at the Taipei City Hall party,
我 父 親 在 公 會 堂 的 慶 祝 晚 會 上
my father raised his arms high.
高 舉 著 手
He said that the time has come
他 說 我 們 做 自 己 主 人 的 時 代
for us to be our own masters.
已 經 到 了
In that picture,
在 那 張 照 片 裡
my father wore an overcoat with a mandarin jacket.
我 看 到 我 父 親 穿 著 長 神 馬 褂
He looked glad and confident,
還 有 那 種 歡 喜 ， 自 信
so full of life.
有 力 的 表 情
I'll never forget that.
我 永 遠 都 記 得
Tsai Chung-Lin,
當 時 在 新 竹 擔 任 火 車 司 機 的
a Hakka train conductor in Hsinchu at the time,
客 家 人 蔡 宗 霾
had this to say about the KMT government
在 2001 年 的 花 談 中
at an interview in 2001.
對 於 國 民 政 府 有 這 樣 的 描 述
Taiwan is returned to its fatherland.
既 然 說 是 我 們 的 祖 國
Our fatherland should do something
對 我 們 的 生 活
to make our lives better.
就 應 該 要 有 所 改 善 才 對
But the Chinese troops
沒 想 結 果 中 國 的 軍 隊
care nothing for the law.
一 來 到 台 灣 就 無 法 無 天
When the Japanese ruled us,
以 前 日 本 政 府 統 治 我 們
it was called colonization.
叫 做 殖 氏
With the KMT government,
現 在 國 民 政 府
it's still colonization.
變 成 了 次 殖 氏
Of course the people are angry.
人 民 自 然 愛 到 怎 氣 沖 天
Once I drove the train
有 一 回 我 開 著 火 車
through the Hukou Station in Hsinchu.
經 過 新 竹 湖 口 站 那 邊
There is a big slope there.
那 邊 是 一 個 大 斡 坡
The station supervisor was signaling me
站 務 長 遠 遠 的 在 那 邊 打 信 號
to stop from afar.
史 我 停 車
He ran up and told me that
他 跑 上 來 說
a soldier needed to get on.
有 一 個 阿 兵 哥 要 坐 車
Just for one person.
一 個 而 已 喔
I didn't want to do it,
我 不 想 要 理 他 啡
but he begged me
可 是 那 個 站 務 長 拜 託 我 說
and said that the soldier threatened him.
他 說 那 個 阿 兵 哥 威 脅 他
If the train didn't stop
如 果 我 車 子 沒 有 停 下 來
he would gather some people
他 就 會 回 去 帶 一 大 票 人 來
and shoot me dead.
然 後 把 我 槍 薩
He got on and sat
他 一 上 來
on the seat next to me.
就 坐 在 我 旁 邊 的 位 子 上 面
The train went up the slope,
後 來 火 車 爬 坡
but couldn't make it over.
慢 慢 爬 不 上 去
I asked everybody to help push the train,
我 請 大 家 幫 忙 推 車
but he just sat there.
他 還 是 坐 在 那 邊
During the Japanese Occupation,
在 日 本 統 治 的 時 代
the soldiers weren't like that,
﹣ 芎 白 本 ﹣ 奇 ﹣ 需 P 蓋 ﹣ 珠 ﹣ 砵
no matter how high their ranks were.
也 沒 有 人 是 這 樣 子 胡 來 的 嘛
People help each other.
大 家 幫 怠 一 下
Chen Yi was appointed Chief Executive
陳 儀 被 派 任 為 台 灣 行 政 長 官
and Garrison Commander of Taiwan.
又 兼 任 警 備 總 司 令
He had visited the island in 1935
他 在 一 九 三 五 年 曾 到 台 灣 誠 問
and highly praised the way
對 日 本 殖 民 地 的 統 治 方 式
the Japanese ruled it.
十 分 推 崇
He believed that the key to success lied in
尤 其 認 為 政 } 其 認 為 政 府 總 攬 經 濟 資 源
the government's control of economic resources.
是 成 功 的 條 件
So, in addition to holding
因 此 台 灣 省 行 政 長 官 公 署
administrative, legislative, judicial,
除 了 集 行 政 ， 立 法 ， 司 法
and military power,
及 軍 事 大 權 於 一 身 之 外
the Taiwan Provincial Governor Office took over
也 把 日 本 人 留 在 台 灣 的
large and medium enterprises left by the Japanese.
中 大 壅 鈍 業 收 歸 國 營
Political, economical
吳 沉 謝 台 心 E 殳 # 吾 ﹣ 炵 栽 2 落 ﹣
and social resources were
社 會 資 源
systematically monopolized.
便 受 到 全 面 性 有 計 畫 的 壟 斷
Although the KMT government
國 民 政 府 雖 然 在 名 義 上
allowed the Taiwanese people to participate in politics,
給 了 台 灣 人 參 政 的 機 會
in actuality,
實 際 上
they denied many well-educated
卻 以 台 灣 沒 有 政 治 人 才 為 藉 口
Taiwanese citizens
或 者 以
from serving high government posts
台 胞 不 解 國 語 國 文 為 理 由
on reasons that they did not speak Mandarin
許 多 受 過 艮 好 教 育 的 台 灣 人
or that Taiwan did not have any political talents.
便 無 法 擔 任 政 府 中 的 高 級 職 位
On October 28, 1946, an editorial in the
1946 年 10 月 28 日
Taiwan People's Newspaper titled
民 報 中 的 社 論
“Preventing the Yearend Crisis” said
要 預 防 年 底 的 危 機 就 明 白 指 出
Everyday, I see promising young men
每 天 看 見
going about looking for jobs.
求 職 的 有 為 青 年 東 奔 西 走
They call on seniors and friends.
草 前 輩 ， 尋 朋 友
They all sighed,
莫 不 長 呼 短 噴
shaking their heads and say it's just the way it is.
搖 頭 吐 氣 說 是 沒 法 子
All the important heads of the government,
﹝ 託 明 宗 街 不 論 是 官 衙 ， 公 司
companies and factories
工 廠 的 大 把 交 椅
were people they do not know.
都 被 陌 生 的 大 哥 坐 滿
This was what Chen Feng-Yuan,
當 時 參 與
who participated in the
台 灣 俸 託 公 司 籌 備 的 陳 逢 源
establishment of Taiwan Trust,
在 1991 年 的 茲 問 紀 錄 中
said at a 1991 interview.
有 這 樣 的 一 段 談 話
When Taiwan was retroceded
台 灣 剛 光 復 的 時 候
we were all very happy.
大 家 都 很 歡 喜
But later we were disappointed.
但 是 接 收 之 後 卻 讓 大 家 很 失 望
Many government officials were corrupt.
接 收 的 官 員 很 多 都 貪 污
We all said that the take-over
台 灣 人 都 說
was literally taking over everything we own.
﹁ 接 收 」 就 像 是 ﹁ 勃 收 」 一 樣
News of corruptions were common at the time.
當 時 大 大 小 小 的 貪 污 新 聞
At the Taiwan Provincial Senate,
王 滇 灸 和 林 日 高 需 位 參 議 員
Congressmen Wang Tien-Teng and Lin Ji-Kao exposed
在 台 灣 省 參 議 會
the crime of embezzlement of goods and materials
揭 露 專 賣 局 和 貿 易 局 兩 位 局 長
by directors of the Monopoly Bureau and Trade Bureau.
吞 沒 數 千 萬 元 台 幣 的 接 收 物 資
Chen Yi cares very much
陳 儀 長 官 很 關 心 台 灣 同 胞
about the Taiwanese people.
開 口 閉 口 都 是 台 灣 同 胞
Taiwanese people are grateful
對 於 長 官 的 關 懷
for his concerns.
台 灣 同 胞 是 非 常 愕 激 的
But unfortunately,
但 是 很 不 幸 的
most of the officials aren't like him.
那 些 接 收 大 員 不 關 心 台 灣 同 胞
All they care about is the money Taiwan can bring them.
他 們 關 心 的 是 台 灣 糖 包
Did you know that the Monopoly Bureau
﹣ 杆 ﹤ 科 ﹥ ﹣ 夾 = 節 ﹣ 奏 ﹣ 客 ﹒ 八
reimbursed 70 kilos of opium?
報 銷 七 十 公 斤 鴉 片 這 件 事 情
I heard they were eaten by termites.
聽 說 是 給 白 蟻 吃 掉 的
If that's the case,
既 然 是 被 白 蟻 吃 摔 的
then I suggest we call
那 麼 我 提 議
a few well-known scientists and doctors
請 幾 位 權 威 的 科 學 家 和 醫 生
to check and see
來 檢 驗
if termites indeed eat opium.
看 白 蟹 是 不 是 真 的 會 吃 掉 鴉 片
Later it was proved that they don't.
事 後 證 明 白 蟹 不 吃 鴉 片
It was eaten up by what the people call Big Tigers
鴉 片 是 被 民 間 所 謔 稱 的
or high officials with power and influence.
﹁ 大 官 虎 」 吃 推 了
After the KMT took over,
國 府 接 管 台 灣 後
with the expansion of state-run enterprises bigger
由 於 公 營 事 業 的 擴 大
than these under Japanese Occupation
遠 超 遇 日 治 時 期 的 獨 佔 企 業
and the corruption of government officials,
再 加 上 官 場 貪 污 舞 弊 作 風
the guidance of amateurs leaders,
外 行 領 導 內 行
led to bad management.
以 致 經 營 不 善
Prices soared;
物 價 飛 漲 一 發 不 可 收 拾
the economy recessed;
經 濟 蕭 條
people lived in destitution;
民 生 凋 敝
thefts were commonplace;
社 會 上 盎 賊 四 起
public security worsened;
治 安 惡 化
and violence existed everywhere.
晷 戾 之 氣 充 斥 各 角 落
Things were getting out of control.
漸 漸 失 控
Get him.
把 他 抓 起 來
Arrest him.
抓 起 來
What are you doing?
幹 什 麼
Is this a revolt?
造 反 啊 你
What revolt?
什 麼 造 反
I don't know what you're talking about.
說 什 麼 我 聽 不 懂 啦
Let go...
放 手 …
Let go of what? I don't understand.
放 什 麼 ， 聽 不 懂 啡
Are you picking on we Taiwanese?
欺 負 台 灣 人 啊
Hey.
仁 峪 ﹣
Hey what?
喂 什 麼
Hey, I don't understand.
喂 我 聽 不 懂 啡
Hey.
仁 峪 ﹣
Don't pick on us.
欺 負 台 灣 人
Guns...
拿 槍 了 …
Under such hard condition,
在 妖 此 生 活 不 易 的 情 況 下
misunderstandings between the Taiwanese and mainlanders
本 島 人 和 大 陸 人 之 間 的 誤 解
are getting worse and worse.
透 漸 加 深
After 50 years of colonization,
經 過 五 十 年 日 本 統 治 的 台 灣
Taiwan had adopted many Japanese characteristics.
東 洋 氣 息 瀰漫
How they speak and behave
在 言 談 舉 止
and how they treat each other
待 人 處 世 各 方 面
were influenced by the Japanese people.
已 相 當 程 度 的 日 本 化
The Chinese soldiers,
這 些 濃 厚 的 東 洋 氣 息
who had just fought the eight-year war,
看 在 剛 打 完 八 年 抗 戰 的
did not like
大 陸 人 士 眼 裡
this foreign flair.
非 常 的 不 以 為 然
They said that the Taiwanese people
於 是 以 ﹁ 奴 化 」 的 字 睦
behaved like slaves.
加 在 台 灣 人 身 上
The Taiwanese resented the mainlanders
台 灣 人 被 指 為 ﹁ 奴 化 」 後
even more after that
對 外 省 人 更 加 反 感
and this turned into a vicious cycle.
形 成 惡 性 循 環
After 50 years of Japanese rule,
台 灣 人 息 遇 日 本 統 治 五 十 年 後
barriers against mainland culture
對 來 自 對 岸 的 祖 國 文 化
appeared
也 已 經 產 生 隔 闐
resulting in maladjustment.
適 廳 不 良 的 狀 況
Friction between the two groups
大 陸 人 與 台 灣 本 地 人 之 間
worsened gradually.
隔 閤 與 摩 擦 日 益 加 深
During a search for illegal cigarettes,
在 一 次 查 緝 私 煙 衝 突 中
the mounting tension
台 灣 人 與 祖 國 之 間 累 積 的 衝 突
finally erupted into
終 於 整 個 爆 發 開 來
a tragedy in the history of Taiwan.
成 為 台 灣 歷 史 上 的 大 悲 劇
Come and buy some.
來 喔 ， 來 買 喔
Come and buy some steamed buns.
來 買 包 子 喔
Buy some sweet fruit.
買 甜 的 水 果 喔
Come on.
來 買 喔
On the evening of February 27, 1947,
1947 年 2 月 27 日 偲 晚
Fu Hsueh-Tung and five anti-smuggling officers
專 賣 賣 局 台 北 分 局 緝 私 員
of the Monopoly Bureau,
傅 學 通 等 六 人
were on duty in Taiping District, Taipei
在 台 北 市 太 平 町
which is now Nanking West Road.
現 在 的 南 京 西 路 一 常 查 緝 私 莢
They found Lin Chiang-Mai, a middle-aged widow,
查 獲 中 年 寡 婦 林 江 邁
selling illegal cigarettes in front of Tian Ma Tea House.
在 天 馬 茶 房 前 販 賣 私 菸
The officers wanted
查 縉 員 要 沒 收
to confiscate the cigarettes
林 江 邁 莎 攤 的 香 菸
and all the money she had with her.
及 身 上 的 金 錢
Lin begged them
林 婦 菩 苺 衰 求
not to do so.
不 讓 他 們 沒 收
They hit her head with their guns
查 緝 員 以 槍 管 敲 打 林 婧 頭 部
until she fell on the ground
造 成 她 頭 部 出 血
bleeding and crying with pain.
倒 在 地 上 含 號
Witnesses were enraged
圍 觀 民 眾 見 狀 後 群 情 激 憤
and protested against the officers,
含 查 緝 員 抗 議
who ran away in panic
查 緝 員 鯨 皇 逃 避
firing their guns to show their authority.
還 邊 開 槍 示 姥
A bystander Chen Wen-His was unfortunately shot
卻 不 幸 擊 中 旁 觀 的 市 民 陳 文 溪
and killed, which further angered the crowd.
民 眾 更 加 氣 憤
They surrounded police and military police stations
包 圍 了 警 局 和 憲 兵 隆
and demanded them to hand over the perpetrator,
要 求 交 出 肇 禍 人 員
but to no avail.
但 沒 有 結 果
Police murderer.
譫 察 打 死 人
Hand over the perpetrator.
交 出 凶 手
On the morning of the 28th,
28 日 上 午
people gathered outside the
群 眾 聚 集 在
Monopoly Bureau to protest.
專 賣 局 台 北 分 局 外 抗 議
They threw paperwork and office supplies
並 將 辦 公 室 內 許 多 公 文 ， 器 具
out onto the street and burned them.
扔 到 馬 路 上 焚 燒
They also beat up a couple of employees.
並 打 傷 幾 名 職 員
Burn them all.
都 把 它 燒 摔 啡
Come on.
核 ﹣
Later in the afternoon, the crowd moved onto
下 午 群 眾 集 結 於
the square in front of the Taiwan Provincial Governor Office.
行 政 長 官 公 署 前 廣 場 示 威 請 顧
The military police on the building's balcony
憲 兵 公 署 陽 台 上 的 憲
swept the crowd with machine guns
竟 用 機 槍 向 民 眾 掃 射
and dozens of people were killed.
死 傷 數 十 人
By now,
陬 J 比
things were already out of control.
事 態 一 發 不 可 收 拾
The city was in an uproar;
全 市 騷 動
shops were closed;
商 店 關 門
factories were shot down;
工 廠 停 工
students refused to go to school.
學 生 罷 課
The Taiwan Garrison Command imposed martial law.
譫 備 總 司 令 部 宣 布 戒 嚴
Young people went to radio stations
青 年 民 眾 進 入 廣 播 電 台
to broadcast the story on air
向 全 省 廣 播 事 情 發 生 的 原 委
and asked people everywhere to work together.
並 呼 籲 各 地 民 眾 起 來 響 應
Today, the 28th of February,
今 天 2 月 28 日
people went to the Governor Office to protest.
我 們 同 胞 一 起 去 長 官 公 署 抗 議
Chen Yi and his administration
陳 儀 政 府
should fire at them with machine guns
竟 然 用 機 關 槍 掃 射 我 們 的 隊 伍
and kill our people.
當 場 打 死 我 們 的 同 胞
Retribution!
賠 償 人 命
Hand over the perpetrator!
交 出 凶 手
From March 1st,
3 月 1 日 起
the protest quickly spread across the island.
事 件 迂 速 擴 及 全 台
Angry crowds attacked the Governor Office
憤 愍 的 群 眾 攻 擊 官 署 警 局
and police stations, and beat up mainlanders,
毅 打 大 陸 人
venting the anger that have built up over the year.
發 洩 一 年 多 來 的 怨 氣
Chen Yi declared martial law.
陳 儀 宣 布 戒 嚴
The military and police fired guns to subdue the crowds
軍 議 開 槍 鎮 壓 民 眾
and you could hear news
處 處 都 可 以 聽 到
of casualties anytime.
軍 議 與 民 眾 傷 亡 的 消 息
In order to appease the anger,
為 了 平 息 事 件
the KMT representatives
3 月 1 日
and congressmen established
由 國 民 參 政 員
the Tobacco Search Murder Investigation Committee
及 省 參 議 員 等 民 意 代 表
on March 1st.
組 成 緝 茂 衄 案 調 查 委 員 會
In order to abate the people's discontent
陳 儀 為 了 緩 和 台 灣 人 民 的 不 滿
and to win time to mobilize troops,
更 為 了 爭 取 時 間 調 兵 鎮 壓
Chen Yi agreed to form
答 懋 組 成 一 個
a committee of the 228 Incident
二 二 八 事 件 處 理 委 員 會
to serve as the mediator
由 處 理 委 員 會 居 間 協 商
and to tell the people
呼 籲 各 地 民 眾
not to hurt mainlanders.
不 可 胡 亂 毆 打 外 省 人
By March 5th,
所 以 到 了 3 月 5 日
except for the Chiayi area,
除 了 嘉 義 一 常 之 外
most of the uproars have quieted down.
各 地 的 騷 動 已 逐 漸 平 息
But Chiang Kai-Shek, head of the KMT,
但 南 京 的 國 民 政 府 主 席 蔣 介 石
after hearing biased statements
聽 信 在 台 匠 台 軍 政 特 務 人 員 的
from secret agents in Taiwan,
一 面 之 詞
still decided to send troops to the island.
仍 然 決 定 派 兵 來 台
Everybody.
各 位
Please calm down.
各 位 請 肅 靜
Please listen to me.
請 大 家 肅 靜 聽 我 說
During a chaotic meeting
3 月 7 日
on March 7th,
處 理 委 員 會 在 混 亂 的 會 議 中
the committee passed the 32 Management Outlines
通 遇 宣 傳 部 長 王 淚 灸 所 提 的
proposed by Wang Tien-Teng, the director of information.
三 十 二 條 處 理 大 網
Which offered concrete resolutions
提 出 具 體 善 後 處 理 方 案
and political reform proposals.
和 政 治 改 革 方 案
After the meeting, the committee took the outlines
會 後 處 委 會 到 長 官 公 署
to Chen Yi at the Governor Office.
向 陳 儀 提 出 處 理 大 網 的 要 求
Chen threw them on the ground,
陳 儀 將 之 擲 地
Rejecting them in anger,
震 態 拒 絕
because he knew that
因 為 他 知 道
the troops from Nanjing were arriving soon.
南 京 派 來 的 軍 隊 將 拯 達 台 灣
On the evening of March 8th,
3 月 8 日 傍 晚
KMT troops landed at Keelung.
國 府 派 來 的 軍 隊 在 基 隆 登 陸
Workers working at the harbor
當 時 正 在 磊 頭 工 作 的 工 人
were shot dead by these men
莫 名 其 妖 遭 到
who appeared out of nowhere.
突 如 其 來 的 軍 隊 掃 射
On March 9th,
3 月 9 日
the 21st Division entered Taipei
二 十 一 師 進 入 台 北
and traveled south,
繼 而 向 南 挺 進
suppressing and killing people everywhere.
在 各 地 展 開 鎮 壓 和 屠 殺
The casualties were heavy.
死 傷 慮 重
The 228 Incident Committee
二 二 八 事 件 處 理 委 員 會
was later proclaimed to be illegal
隨 即 被 陳 儀 宣 布 為 非 法 組 纓
and dissolved by Chen Yi.
而 被 命 解 散
Many of the social elites who participated in the meeting
參 與 開 會 的 許 多 社 會 領 導 精 莢
were in the purge list.
也 開 始 被 列 為 清 算 整 肅 的 對 象
They either disappeared or were murdered.
最 後 莫 名 的 失 蹤 或 遭 到 殘 殺
On March 20th,
3 月 20 日
the Governor Office began
甘 官 公 署 開 始 在 全 島 各 地
what was called the "countryside cleansing,” to
展 開 所 謂 的 ﹁ 清 鄉 」 行 動
threaten people to turn in weapons and perpetrators
以 連 坐 法 的 威 脢
or to suffer collateral punishment.
要 求 民 眾 交 出 武 器 和 ﹁ 惡 人 」
People were either arrested or shot,
各 地 不 斷 有 人 被 捕 槍 殺
all without open trials.
而 且 都 沒 有 經 公 開 審 判
Taiwan was shrouded under
台 灣 到 處 充 斥 著
a murderous atmosphere.
冷 冽 的 肅 殺 氣 氛
To this day, the exact
二 二 八 事 件 期 間
number of casualties
多 少 人
is still uncertain.
至 今 仍 然 沒 有 精 確 定 論
According to the Executive Yuan,
不 過 根 據 行 政 院 公 布 的
the official investigation
官 方 調 查 報 告
puts the death toll at roughly 10,000 to 20,000.
死 亡 人 數 約 在 一 萬 至 兩 萬 人
The 228 Incident resulted in
二 二 八 事 件 幪 給 台 灣 的
more than just broken families.
明 家 破 人 ﹣ 亢 的 悲 師 j 君 巳 ﹒
The hatred and contradiction
族 群 間 埋 下 的 怨 恨 與 矛 盾
Planted in the two groups deeply affected
深 深 影 響 到
Taiwan's future political trajectory.
台 灣 後 來 的 政 治 走 向
Years afterwards,
事 過 境 遷
many post-war literary works
在 戰 後 的 台 灣 文 學 中
of Taiwan still focus on
許 多 作 品
the 228 Incident, voicing
仍 然 以 二 二 八 事 件 為 題 材
the sorrow of the people.
普 遍 表 達 出 台 灣 人 民 的 哀傷
After 1949, the situation
1949 年 以 後 的 台 灣
in Taiwan was no better.
天 窕 更 加 灰 暗
The tragedies didn't stop.
悲 劇 也 尚 未 終 結
The KMT government,
國 民 黨 政 府
through tightly organized
藉 由 組 織 嚴 密 的
intelligence system and secret agents stationed
情 治 系 統 和 特 務
in government offices and schools,
由 城 市 到 鄉 村
from cities to countryside,
撤 下 密 不 通 風 的 天 羅 地 網
strictly monitored the society
嚴 密 監 控 著 整 個 著 社 會
to curb and eliminate
藉 此 整 肅 異 己
any dissidents, and to
掃 除 異 議 份 子
strengthen its supreme power.
鞏 固 自 身 至 高 無 上 的 權 力
Various powers existed in Taiwan
原 有 的 台 灣 各 種 勢 力
were reorganized.
都 被 重 新 整 頓
They aggressively trained
他 們 也 積 極 培 養
a pro-KMT faction,
扶 植 親 國 民 黨 的 派 系 勢 力
and successfully created a monopolized
完 成 了 在 台 灣
and authoritative party in Taiwan.
一 黨 獨 大 的 黨 國 威 權 體 制
So when people were busy,
所 以 人 們 忙 碣 的 時 候
they still remembered Ah Q.
也 還 記 起 阿 Q 來
But they remembered his deeds
然 而 記 起 的 是 做 工
and not his background.
並 不 是 行 狀
What do you guys think about that?
﹣ 莖 ﹤ 志 1 亙 基 3 琢 ﹥ 堅 L ﹣ 女 ﹥ ﹣foJ
That's us, isn't it?
這 不 就 是 我 們 嗣
Ah Q...
阿 Q﹒﹒﹒
We're like Ah Q.
我 們 就 像 阿 Q
Frogs at the bottom of a well.
二 底 之 蛙
He says that Ah Q
他 說 阿 Q 的 眼 裡
is not someone's...
不 是 別 人 一 個 眼 裡 的 …
Who is it?
是 誰
A Hakka young man named Chen Chuan-Chih
客 家 青 年 陳 傳 枝
was arrested for attending a study group.
當 時 困 為 參 加 讀 書 會 被 捕
The records of a 2001 interview showed
在 2001 年 的 花 談 記 錄 中
this version of what happened.
有 閡 樣 的 說 法
At that time,
當 時
people didn't understand how the KMT could have been
大 家 對 國 民 黨 接 收 美 軍
driven to Taiwan by the Communist Party
這 麼 好 的 裝 備
with the advanced equipment
還 讓 共 產 黨 逼 退 來 到 台 灣
the KMT took over from the Americans.
感 到 不 脊 理 解
But once they understood,
一 日 瞭 解 了
they resented the society.
就 對 社 會 不 滿
Those secret agents are abominable.
那 些 抓 人 的 特 務 實 在 很 可 惡
Not only did they arrest the
為 了 錕
people at the study group,
不 但 將 讀 書 會 的 人 批 走
they also arrested their
也 把 他 們 的 好 朋 友
friends, for money.
通 通 批 走
Some people didn't even know how to read.
有 的 人 連 書 都 沒 讀 過
Under the pressure from the KMT,
當 時 在 國 民 黨 的 壓 力 下
both Taiwanese and
不 論 是 外 省 的 ， 本 省 的
mainlanders were arrested.
全 都 有 人 被 抓
One of these men
其 中 有 一 個 人
was Lee Jui-Tung.
史 做 李 瑞 東 先 生
He taught them by writing on soaps with chopsticks.
他 用 筷 子 當 筆
If someone was sick,
要 是 有 人 生 病 了
he would give him medicine.
他 還 會 拿 藥 給 他 們
The intellectuals who
那 個 時 候
were executed at that time.
被 人 槍 決 的 知 識 份 子
Were cultivated people with
他 們 的 人 品 ， 修 養
good personalities.
全 都 是 一 等 一 的
Chen Chuan-Chih, a train conductor
像 火 車 司 機 陳 傳 枝
like about 2000 political victims
這 樣 在 白 色 恐 怖 中 的
of White Terror,
政 治 受 難 者
were executed.
大 約 有 兩 千 人 遭 到 槍 決
More than 8000 people received heavy sentences.
八 千 多 人 被 判 重 刑
Among them, less than 900
其 中 不 到 九 百 人
were real Communists.
是 冀 正 的 共 產 黨 員
The remaining 9000 or so cases
其 他 九 千 多 人
were either unjust, misjudged or feigned.
都 是 冤 案 ， 錯 案 或 假 案
Of all the people who were killed,
這 些 死 亡 名 單 中
two-thirds were Taiwanese
本 省 籍 佔 三 分 之 二
and one-third were mainlanders.
外 省 籍 佔 三 分 之 一
In the 50s, outside the Taipei Train Station,
50 年 代 的 台 北 火 車 站 前
on bulletin boards,
布 告 牌 上 常 常 公 布 著 一 堆 名 單
it was common to see lists of names with red checks
用 紅 筆 打 勾 的
suggesting people being executed for mutiny.
表 示 因 ﹁ 叛 亂 罪 」 而 遭 槍 決
Young people from different ethnicities and provinces
這 些 被 害 人 不 分 族 群 和 省 籍
were often accused of crimes they did not commit,
常 常 在 莫 須 有 的 罪 名 下
costing their young lives,
葬 逆 了 自 己 的 青 春
and sometimes even the lives
甚 至 生 命
and the happiness of their families.
還 有 家 人 的 幸 福
In December 1950,
1950 年 12 月
a young man from Banciao named Lin Ju-Yu
一 位 板 橋 青 年 林 姜 堵
was executed at Machang District,
在 現 在 青 年 公 園 的 馬 場 町
what is now the Youth Park.
遭 槍 決
His sister Lin Hsin-Tzu recalls the execution.
他 的 妹 妹 林 俸 子 回 憶 說
On Saturday,
1950 年 12 月 16 日
December 16, 1950,
星 期 ˋ 計
at around 7 o'clock in the morning,
早 上 七 點 鐘 巨 右
I took the train as usual
我 像 平 常 一 樣
from Banciao to go to school in Taipei.
從 板 橋 搭 火 車 到 台 北 上 學
As I walked out of the platform,
當 我 走 出 月 台 時
I saw a crowd gathering
看 到 台 北 火 車 站 前 的 告 示 牌
in front of the bulletin board at the Taipei Train Station.
又 擠 滿 了 圍 觀 的 群 眾
With a feeling of uneasiness,
我 懷 著 一 股 莫 名 ， 不 安 的 心 情
I slowly walked up to it.
走 上 前 去
From afar,
我 遠 遠 地
I saw the list of so-called "mutineers."”
就 看 到 了 那 所 謂 ﹁ 叛 亂 犯 」
On one of the lines
霓 密 麻 麻 的 死 刑 者 榜 單 上
was the name Lin Ju-Yu.
林 如 埼
Aged 28
二 十 入
Death penalty.
死 刑
I was devastated, and didn't know
我 心 中 的 悲 痘
whether I should cry or
一 時 之 間 不 知 道 要 哭
I should just turn and leave.
只 是 茬 然 地 轉 身 離 開
In 1949,
1949 年
on May 20th,
民 國 38 年 5 月 20 日
Provincial Government Chairman Chen Cheng
台 灣 省 主 席 陳 該
announced martial law for Taiwan.
頒 布 了 台 灣 地 區 的 戒 嚴 令
For 38 years,
從 此 台 灣 進 入 了
the island lived under strict governance.
長 達 三 十 八 年 的 戒 嚴
Six months after
半 年 後
the KMT was defeated in China.
在 中 國 大 陸 失 去 了 政 權 的
The republic government
中 華 民 國 政 府
retreated to Taiwan
帶 領 著 大 約 九 十 多 萬 軍 民
with about 900,000 soldiers and civilians.
撤 守 台 灣
This was a rare
在 台 灣 歷 史 上
mass immigration
這 是 一 次 極 為 竿 見 的
in the history of the island.
大 規 模 移 民 潮
As a result, Taiwan's population structure
使 得 台 灣 的 人 口 結 構
changed quantitatively and qualitatively.
產 生 了 量 變 和 質 變
Different cultures in this island
多 元 文 化 的 發 展
once again changed and
又 再 一 次 在 這 個 海 島 上
conflict with one another.
進 行 相 互 的 激 盪 和 改 變
This added diversity to Taiwan
有 / 訝 了 更 豐 富 的 面 貌
and had a great impact
也 對 台 灣 社 會
on the Taiwanese society.
造 成 極 大 的 衝 擊 和 影 響
Henceforth, the republic government
從 此 中 華 民 國 政 府
took over Taiwan, Penghu, Kinmen, and Matsu.
固 守 台 澎 金 馬
The civil war was henceforth
於 是 國 共 之 間 的 內 戰
fought across the Taiwan Strait.
隔 著 一 條 台 灣 海 峽 繼 續 開 打
Taiwan, Penghu, Kinmen and Matsu
台 澎 金 馬
became world-famous
成 為 一 個 舉 世 聞 名 的
anti-Communist and anti-Soviet fortresses.
反 共 抗 俄 的 堡 壇
The 6 million people who lived in Taiwan,
而 原 本 在 台 灣 的
soldiers and civilians alike,
也 成 為 蔣 介 石 口 中 的
became Chiang Kai-Shek's anti-communist
全 國 軍 民 同 胞 們
and anti-Soviet subjects
嘆 崗 謝
who would give up their lives for their country.
反 共 抗 俄 的 子 民
After every speech Chiang makes,
在 蔣 介 石 每 次 的 演 講 之 後
he would lead the people on the square
都 會 率 領 廣 場 上 的 軍 民 同 胞 們
to shout "Long live the Republic.”
高 喊 著 中 華 民 國 萬 歲 ， 萬 萬 歲
The people below would then shout
台 下 的 民 眾 也 會 接 著 高 喊
"Long live President Chiang."
蔣 總 統 萬 歲 ， 萬 萬 歲
Long live the Republic!
中 華 民 國 萬 歲
Once in Nanjing, Chiang Kai-Shek announced
蔣 介 石 曾 經 在 南 京 公 布 一 個
the Temporary Provisions Effective During the Period
凍 結 憲 法 部 分 條 文 的
of Communist Rebellion which froze a portion of the constitution.
動 員 戡 亂 時 期 憲 法 臨 時 條 款
After the relocation of KMT in Taiwan,
到 了 台 灣 之 後
the provisions were amended
這 個 臨 時 條 款 再 經 修 改
to expand presidential power.
使 得 總 統 權 力 擴 充
Consequently, Chiang served five terms,
蔣 介 石 也 因 此 連 續 做 了 五 任
or 25 years, as president.
甘 達 二 十 五 年 的 總 統
Taiwan, as an interim government under
在 這 種 高 舉 著 ﹁ 反 共 拔 俄 」 的
the banner of anti-Communist and anti-Soviet,
蠶 時 體 制 下 的 中 華 民 國
was actually under an autocratic rule
其 實 是 一 個
of coercion.
政 治 上 高 壓 管 控 的 獨 裁 體 制
Basic human rights and human dignity
基 本 人 權 和 人 性 尊 嚴
were greatly suppressed.
難 到 極 度 壓 投
Meanwhile, the shadow of war
而 戰 爭 的 陰 影
still shrouded over Taiwan.
也 一 直 籠 罩 在 台 灣 上 空
On January 20, 1955.
1955 年 1 月 20 日
The Korean War had just ended.
韓 戰 才 結 束 不 久
Taiwan became a vital stronghold
台 灣 已 經 是
in the US's efforts to combat Communism.
美 國 圍 墬 共 黨 勢 力 的 重 要 據 點
The Communist Party attacked Yijiangshan Islands,
中 共 揮 軍 攻 打
where some KMT troops stationed.
仍 騮 有 國 軍 的 一 江 山 鵠
The US Congress immediately passed the Formosa Resolution
美 國 國 會 立 國 會 立 即 通 過 台 灣 決 議 案
to show its determination in defending Taiwan.
宣 示 美 國 防 衛 台 灣 的 決 心
Yet they still hoped that Chiang Kai-Shek
但 是 仍 希 望 蔣 介 石
would leave the islands off the coast of Fujien,
自 福 建 外 海 離 島
and retreat from Dachen and Zhoushan Islands.
如 大 陳 ， 舟 山 群 島 撤 軍
Chiang took the US's advice
蔣 介 石 總 統 接 受 了 美 國 的 建 議
of relinquishing the islands,
放 棄 大 陳 島 ， 舟 山 群 島
but the US continued to pressure him
但 是 美 國 繼 續 壓 迫 蔣 介 石
to withdraw from Kinmen and Matsu.
自 金 門 ， 馬 祖 撤 兵
But this time, Chiang did not comply.
這 次 蔣 介 石 並 本 接 受
On August 23, 1958,
1958 年 8 月 23 日
the PRC resumed their attacks on Kinmen and Matsu.
申 共 又 再 度 對 金 門 ， 馬 祖 砲 擊
More than 40,000 bombs were dropped in a two hours.
兩 小 時 內 落 彈 四 萬 餘 發
Thus beganthe the Aug. 23rd Artillery Bombardment.
八 二 三 砲 戰 就 此 爆 發
During the 44 days
砲 戰 持 續 四 十 四 天
of the bombardment,
這 段 期 間
the 40 some square meters of Kinmen
四 十 多 平 方 公 里 的 金 門
was hit 47,000 times.
遭 砲 擊 四 十 七 萬 發
After the battle broke out,
砲 戰 爆 發 後
the US provided goods and armament assistance
美 國 提 供 物 資 與 武 器 的 資 助
and escorted supplies to the frontline,
以 及 補 給 線 上 的 護 航
but avoided any direct interference.
但 極 力 避 免 直 接 介 入 戰 爭
On October 23, Eisenhower
10 月 23 日
and Chiang Kai-Shek reached an understanding.
芳 森 豪 與 蔣 介 石 雙 方 妥 協
Chiang agreed not to use
蔣 介 石 答 應
armed force to counterattack China.
放 棄 使 用 武 力 反 攻 大 陸
Eisenhower promised to help defense Kinmen and Matsu.
艾 森 豪 則 承 諾
This promise extended
這 個 解 釋
beyond the Mutual Defense Treaty
突 破 了 台 灣 與 美 國
signed by Taiwan and the US.
共 同 防 禦 條 約 範 圍
The Aug. 23rd Artillery Bombardment
入 二 三 砲 戰
gradually concluded with
最 後 由 中 共
the PRC adapting the method
以 ﹁ 單 日 打 雙 日 不 打 」 的 方 式
of attacking only on odd dates.
漸 漸 收 場
But the real conclusion
只 是 這 個 收 場
didn't come until 20 years later.
收 了 約 二 十 年 才 落 幕
The fierce military combat across the strait
兩 岸 也 從 激 烊 的
gradually calms down to
軍 事 對 抗 和 衝 突
a Cold War situation.
漸 漸 成 為 緩 和 的 冷 戰 局 面
With no external conflicts,
使 得 中 華 民 國 政 府
the republic government was then able
以 無 外 顧 之 愛
to exercise authoritative rule on Taiwan
對 內 實 施 威 權 統 治
and to fully develop its economy.
並 全 力 發 展 經 濟
Sharing the hatred for a common enemy
就 在 如 此 同 仇 敵 愣
and having survived critical times,
風 需 飄 搖 的 過 程 中
the people of Taiwan
在 台 灣 的 軍 民 同 胞 們
became an united
已 經 形 成 了 一 個
life community.
團 結 的 生 命 共 同 體
People were educated to call themselves "Chinese,"
而 且 也 被 教 育 成 自 己 是 中 國 人
honorable citizens of a "Free China.”
一 個 ﹁ 自 由 中 國 」 的 光 榮 子 民
They will never reconcile
和 對 岸 的 邪 惡 ﹁ 共 產 中 國 」
with the evil "Communist China.”
勤 不 兩 立
October 31st,
10 月 31 日
is the 70th birthday
是 我 們 偉 大 的 領 袖 蔣 總 統
of our great leader President Chiang.
七 秣 華 誕
The whole country is busy preparing
全 國 同 胞 熱 恬 的 展 開
for various kinds of celebrations.
各 種 祝 壽 活 動
Facing the autocratic rule,
然 而 面 對 威 權 統 治
intellectual liberalists from China
來 自 中 國 的 自 由 主 義 知 識 份 子
such as Lei Zhen and Hu Shi
如 雷 震 ﹒ ， 胡 適 等 人
cried out for freedom and democracy.
爭 取 自 由 ， 民 主 的 呼 聲
They founded the Free China Journal.
創 辦 了 自 由 中 國 雜 誌
In 1956,
在 1956 年
on his 70th birthday, Chiang announced
蔣 介 石 總 統 七 十 歲 大 壽 時
his intension to serve another term.
並 且 表 明 將 要 繼 續 連 任 總 統
Free China Journal released
﹁ 自 由 中 國 」 雜 誌
the "Birthday Celebration Special Issue.”
推 出 的 ﹁ 祝 壽 專 號 」
Hu Shi, Hsu Fu-Kuan, Mao Tse-Shui
胡 適 ， 徐 復 觀 ， 毛 子 水
Hsu Dau-Lin, Chen Chi-Tien, Tao Bai-Chuan,
徐 道 鄰 ， 陳 啟 天 ， 陶 百 川
Chiang Yun-Tien, Hsia Tao-Ping, and Lei Zhen,
蔣 勻 田 ， 夏 道 平 ， 雷 震
are intellectual liberalists from China.
這 群 來 自 中 國 大 陸 的
They took the opportunity
自 由 主 義 知 識 份 子
to propose a self-review
藉 著 這 個 機 會
and to offer their advices to Chiang Kai-Shek.
向 蔣 介 石 總 統 提 出 檢 討 和 建 言
Hu Shi wrote a long essay
胡 適 並 且 發 表 了 長 篇 的 文 章
to tactfully advise Chiang to give up dictatorship,
委 婉 勸 告 蔣 介 石 放 棄 獨 裁
to withdraw his power from the government.
做 到 無 能 ， 無 治 ， 無 為
Other essays advised Chiang
其 他 文 章 則 建 議 蔣 介 石
to select a successor,
選 拔 繼 任 人 才
to establish a cabinet system
磐 立 內 閣 制
and to nationalize the armed forces.
實 施 軍 隊 國 家 化
These advices were meant to
硍 謚
offer the KMT an opportunity
原 本 廳 該 是 給 予 國 民 黨 政 府
to reform itself.
一 個 改 革 的 契 機
But they had exactly the opposite effect
可 是 卻 適 得 其 反
and drew calculated critiques in the KMT
引 來 國 民 黨 政 府 及 軍 方 刊 物
and military periodicals.
有 計 畫 的 批 判
From 1959 to 1960,
到 了 1959 到 1960 年 之 間
Free China Journal further expressed
自 由 中 國 雜 誌
their disapproval of Chiang's interference
更 是 表 達
with the operation of the constitution politics,
反 對 蔣 介 石 破 壤 憲 政 常 軌
making amendments or revising the provisions
以 修 憲 或 修 改 臨 時 條 款
for the purpose of renewing his term.
達 到 繼 續 連 任 總 統 的 目 的
These intellectuals have
這 群 知 識 份 子
in fact slowly reached
其 實 已 經 逐 步 逼 近 到
the KMT's limit.
基 政 當 局 的 最 後 禁 恒
Six months after the publication of
就 在 自 由 中 國 的
Free China Journal's special issue,
祝 壽 專 號 出 刊 半 年 後
Taiwan held its third election
台 灣 舉 行 第 三 屆 縣 市 長
of county and city mayors, and congressmen.
及 省 議 員 的 選 舉
Before the election,
選 前
candidates from other parties joined
在 一 些 本 土 政 治 人 士 的 推 動 下
a meeting on improving election processes
召 開 黨 外 候 選 人
summoned by native politicians.
關 於 選 務 改 進 的 座 談 會
They decided to have
並 決 議
Lee Wan Chu organize
選 後 由 李 萬 居 負 責 盡 速 召 開
an election review forum.
一 個 選 舉 檢 討 座 談 會
On April 21st,
4 月 21 日 的 一 天 裡
voters of both sexes across the island
台 灣 全 省 的 男 女 選 民
eagerly cast their ballots.
紛 紛 參 加 投 票
The turnout rate was over 80%.
總 投 票 率 高 達 百 分 之 八 十 以 上
Taiwan's self-rule
台 灣 的 地 方 自 治
and the democratic politics of a free China
和 自 由 中 國 的 民 主 政 治
took another step forward.
從 此 更 向 前 邁 進 一 步
In this election,
這 次 選 舉
Kuo Kuo-Chi of Taichung,
台 中 市 的 郭 國 基
Wu San-Lien of Tainan,
台 南 縣 的 吳 三 連
Lee Yuan-Chan of Kaohsiung,
高 雄 市 的 李 源 桶
Kuo Yu-Hsin of Yilan,
宜 蘭 縣 的 郭 雨 新
Lee Wan-Chu of Yunlin,
雲 林 縣 的 李 萬 居
and Hsu Shih-Hsien of Chiayi
嘉 義 縣 的 許 世 賢
were elected congressmen.
當 選 省 議 員
They were later referred to
這 便 是 後 來 ﹁ 省 議 會 五 虎 將 」
as the Five Tigersor the Five Dragons and One Phoenix.
及 ﹁ 五 龍 一 鳳 」 稱 號 的 由 來
In 1960, there was another local election.
1960 年 又 逢 地 方 選 舉
On May 18th,
選 舉 後 的 5 月 18 日
Lei Zhen, together with politicians from outside KMT
無 黨 籍 人 士 和 雷 震
and from Chinese Youth Party
及 民 青 兩 黨 人 士
and the China Democratic Socialist Party, 72 in all,
共 七 十 二 人
held a local election review
在 台 北 市 民 社 黨 總 部
for opposition party members and non-partisans
召 間 在 野 黨 及 無 黨 無 派 人 士
at the China Democratic Socialist Party Headquarters,
本 屆 地 方 選 舉 檢 討 會
In the meeting, frauds in the election were criticized.
會 中 激 烈 批 評 選 舉 舞 弊
Kuo Kuo-Chi vehemently declaimed at the review.
郭 國 基 在 會 中 燙 慨 陳 詞
I want to dissolve the Chinese Youth Party
希 望 把 民 青 兩 黨 整 個 全 部 解 散
and the China Democratic Socialist Party,
和 台 灣 一 般 民 主 人 士
and to form a strong opposition party
共 同 來 組 織 一 個
with the democrats of Taiwan
強 而 有 力 的 在 野 黨
to enforce democracy.
發 揮 民 主 的 力 量
pushed the party organization
使 得 組 黨 活 動
into an intense new stage.
進 入 緊 鑽 密 鼓 的 新 階 段
In 1960, the Vietnam War broke out
1960 年 越 戰 爆 發
and Taiwan heightened its anti-communist defense.
國 內 防 共 的 情 勢 更 加 升 高
On September 4th of the same year,
同 年 9 月 4 日
the Taiwan Garrison Command
台 灣 警 備 總 部
arrested Lei Zhen, Fu Zheng,
以 涉 嫌 叛 亂 的 理 由 進 捕 雷 震
editor-in-chief of Free China Journal,
及 自 由 申 國 的 主 編 傅 正
its manager Ma Chih-Su,
經 理 馬 之 駿
and its booker Lei Chi-Yin.
會 計 雷 子 英 等 四 人
Lei Zhen was charged with
雷 震 被 冠 上
"propagating for communists”
散 布 ﹁ 反 攻 無 望 論 」
by sending messages of “hopeless of fighting back"
為 ﹁ 為 匪 宣 傳 」 的 罪 名
and was sentenced to 10 years in jail.
使 得 雷 震 被 判 有 期 徒 刑 十 年
The arrest of Lei Zhen
雷 震 的 被 捕
ended the valuable experience
結 束 了 這 一 段
of Taiwanese and mainlanders
﹁ 本 省 人 」 和 ﹁ 外 省 人 」
working hand in hand
為 台 灣 民 主 政 治 攜 手 奮 鬥 的
to fight for a democratic Taiwan.
可 貴 經 歷
Heartless strikes by the ruler
統 治 者 無 情 的 打 擊
with the Lei Zhen case
也 讓 台 灣 的 民 主 運 動
sunk Taiwan's democratic movement.
困 ﹁ 雷 震 案 」 而 跌 入 谷 底
And Free China Journal
而 ﹁ 自 由 中 國 」
became an irony in history.
反 倒 成 了 歷 史 的 嘴 諷
In addition to suppressing political democracy,
除 了 對 於 民 主 政 治 的 壓 投 之 外
after they arrive Taiwan,
國 民 黨 政 府 來 到 台 灣 之 後
the KMT instilled anti-communist thoughts in the people
透 過 教 育 和 塾 斷 媒 體
through education and media monopoly.
灌 輸 人 民 反 共 思 想
Besides suppressing anything related to local culture
他 們 除 了 打 壓
and local cultural performances,
和 本 土 有 關 的 文 化
the KMT also suppress
限 制 和 本 土 相 關 的 文 化 展 演
any literary arts
更 切 斷 了
connected with socialism
所 有 社 會 主 義 相 關 的 文 學 藝 術
and inhibited the spread of liberal thinking.
也 壓 投 了 自 由 主 羲 思 想 的 傳 播
Furthermore, they ignored the achievements
對 於 日 治 時 代 的
and developments made in Taiwanese literature and art
台 灣 文 學 藝 術 成 就 和 發 展
during Japanese Occupation.
更 是 刻 意 怕 略
Living under
生 活 在 這 樣 一 個
a vacuum state of thinking
思 想 真 空 狀 態 的 台 灣 青 年
and a spoon-fed education system,
在 增 鴨 式 的 教 育 體 系 下
young people of Taiwan spent a large amount of time
花 《 大 量 時 間
memorizing materials about China.
肯 諷 教 科 書 裡 面 的 中 國
However, they didn't identify
卻 普 遍 對 自 己
with the land they lived in
真 實 生 活 的 土 地 和 人 民
and the people they lived with.
缺 乏 誤 同
At that time,
當 時 大 多 數
most university graduates
慮 大 學 教 育 的 知 識 份 子
have two choices before them.
畢 業 之 後 選 擇 的 出 路
They can get into the civil service sector
一 種 是 透 過 各 種 考 試 的 管 道
through various examinations
想 盡 辦 法 進 入 公 務 系 統
for a life of stability.
安 身 立 命
Or they can study abroad,
另 一 種 則 是 選 擇 出 國 留 學
temporarily or permanently leaving Taiwan.
曜 時 或 甚 至 是 永 遠 的 離 開 台 灣
Local concerns were ignored
本 土 情 懷 被 隔 絕
and history and culture were disconnected.
歷 史 文 化 被 斷 裂
American values thus
於 是 以 美 國 價 值 為 主 導 的 文 化
entered the country.
趁 虛 而 入
Bob Hope came to the stage
鮑 伯 賀 佟 坐 著
sitting on a Chinese rickshaw
中 國 的 三 輪 車 出 場
and made the audience crack in laughter.
一 開 始 就 逗 得 全 場 大 笑
During the Vietnam War,
尤 其 是 在 越 戰 期 間
Taiwan became a logistic supply base
台 灣 更 成 為 美 軍 後 勤 補 給 基 地
and a holiday retreat for the American armed forces.
也 成 為 美 軍 休 假 中 心
More than 200,000 Americans visited Taiwan in 10 years.
十 年 間 有 二 十 萬 人 次
A large number of bars and sex shops opened,
大 量 的 酒 吧 和 色 情 行 業 興 起
forming Taiwan's early sex industry.
成 了 台 灣 色 情 業 的 雛 型
Furthermore,
除 此 之 外
Hollywood movies, anti-war songs,
好 萊 堿 的 電 影 ， 反 戰 歌 曲
Coca-Cola, and American radios
可 口 可 樂 和 美 軍 電 台
became fashionable.
成 了 一 種 時 髦 和 流 行
The KMT applied suppression politically,
國 民 黨 政 府 在 政 治 上 施 行 高 壓
but economically they believed in technical experts
但 在 經 濟 上 相 當 授 權 技 術 官 僚
to advance policies and carry out reforms.
推 動 政 策 並 進 行 改 革
People like Yin Chung-Jung,
愛 到 層 峰 信 任 的 尹 余 容
Lee Kuo-Ding
李 國 童
and Yen Chia-Kan were trusted
嚴 家 淦 等
and had much freedom in their duty.
擁 有 相 當 程 度 的 自 主 權
They led in US Aid Council,
而 他 們 主 導 的 美 援 會 ， 經 合 會
International & Economic Cooperation Council,
乃 至 經 濟 部 等 至 經 濟 部 等 財 經 單 位
and Economic Affairs Ministry,
可 以 說 為 日 後 台 灣 的 經 濟 發 展
to help lay basis for later economic progress.
莫 下 堅 實 的 基 磷
They effectively planned and used
他 們 當 時 也 有 效 統 籌 運 用
the funds from the U.S. and foreign exchange
美 援 資 金 及 有 限 外 匯
to properly map out an industrial development plan.
姒 善 規 畫 了 台 灣 產 業 發 展 藍 圖
In the 1960s,
1960 年 代
Taiwan's economy began to transform.
台 灣 的 經 濟 開 始 轉 型
A large part was
很 大 一 部 分 原 囧
due to the implementation of
來 自 於 建 立
an export-oriented economic policy
出 口 導 向 的 經 濟 政 策
and the establishment of an export processing zone.
及 加 工 出 口 區 的 成 立
In 1965,
1965 年
under the suggestion of Lee Kuo-Ding,
在 李 國 鼎 的 率 先 建 議 下
the world's first export processing zone
高 雛 設 立 了
was established in Kaohsiung,
全 球 第 一 個 加 工 出 口 區
allowing production materials
讓 所 有 生 產 材 料
to be imported without taxes
可 以 不 必 課 徵 關 稅 或 其 他 稅 賦
of any kind.
自 由 進 口
All products can be exported freely.
所 有 產 品 也 可 以 自 由 出 口
The Kaohsiung Export Processing Zone
高 雁 加 工 出 口 區
provided inexpensive labor and land,
提 供 雕 價 的 勞 工 及 土 地
tax incentives,
加 上 稅 務 優 惟
and efficient management,
及 有 效 率 的 管 理
to attract many foreign investments
喧 引 許 多 外 國 投 資
and create myriads of job opportunities.
也 創 造 了 大 量 的 就 業 機 會
In addition,
此 外 台 灣 民 間
there were the hard-working
還 有 大 批 無 數 黔 默 耕 耘 的
small and medium-sized business owners.
中 小 伐 業 主
They worked industriously
他 們 辛 勤 的 奮 鬥
to produce and to develop an international market.
生 產 並 開 拓 海 外 市 場
Working with the government,
與 政 府 共 同 創 造 了
they created an economic miracle in Taiwan.
吳 洲 蕙 去 至 # 範 ﹣ ﹣ 鏗 ﹣ 丞 黃
In the global sense,
在 整 個 世 界 經 濟 的 分 工 上
countries like Taiwan, Korea,
台 灣 與 韓 國
Singapore, and Hong Kong,
新 加 坡 ， 香 港
can provide human resources
這 些 人 力 資 源 豐 富
with cheap labor,
工 資 便 宜
and infrastructure.
而 且 又 具 備 基 礎 工 業 的 國 家
In the 1960s
從 1960 年 代 開 始
their economy began to grow
吸 坊 # 範 啁 2 / 算 歧 ﹒ ﹣ 甜 ﹣
and was called Asian Tigers.
被 國 際 譽 為 ﹁ 亞 洲 四 小 龍 」
Industrial development, however,
不 過 工 業 的 發 展
was at the cost of agriculture,
要 以 農 業 為 墊 腳 石
and also sacrificed the ecological environment.
並 且 犧 牲 生 態 環 境
Rural villages provided an abundance of cheap labor.
農 村 提 供 了 充 沛 又 康 價 的 勞 力
Many country girls went to cities for better jobs.
鄉 村 少 女 往 都 市 去 發 展 的 故 事
This is quite common at that time.
正 是 當 時 台 澎 是 當 時 台 灣 社 會 的 寫 照
There's a popular song
有 一 首 在 六 十 年 代 初 期
from the early 60s
最 流 行 的 歌
titled "The Wish of an Orphan Girl."
孤 女 的 願 望
It represented the sound of the people
代 表 來 自 民 間 的 聲 音
and voiced their meager hope.
和 卑 徵 的 願 望
Under heavy oppression,
在 高 壓 統 治 下 的 台 灣 社 會
life then was monotonous, confined and repressed.
呈 現 的 是 單 調 ， 封 閉 與 壓 抑
The original vitality
而 社 會 中
that existed in the society
原 來 就 十 分 強 大 的 生 命 力
was duly directed
卻 在 政 府 財 經 政 策 的 領 航 下
under the government's fiscal policy.
全 力 向 前 快 樂 出 航
Taiwan's future was moving toward a new start.
為 台 灣 的 本 來 找 到 方 向
Taiwan's little league baseball team
中 華 少 棒 隊
with an overwhelming edge
以 壓 倒 性 的 優 勢
easily won championship in
輕 騎 遇 關
Little League World Series.
榮 登 世 界 少 棒 王 座
At two o'clock am of August 20, 1969,
1969 年 8 月 20 日 深 夜 兩 點
most of the people in Taiwan
台 灣 大 多 數 民 眾
were up listening to the radio
都 熬 夜 守 在 收 音 機 旁
broadcasting the Little League World Series game
收 聽 在 美 國 威 床 波 特 舉 行 的
held in Williamsport, Pennsylvania.
世 界 少 棒 賽
When they heard that
當 他 們 聽 到
the Taichung Gold Dragon
來 自 台 中 的 金 龍 少 棒 隊
defeated the U.S. West Division team
擊 敗 美 國 西 區 代 表 隊
and became world champion,
奪 得 世 界 少 棒 賽 的 冠 軍 時
the whole country burst into cheers.
全 國 歡 聲 雷 動
People ran out to the streets and hugged one another.
人 們 衛 上 街 頭 擁 抱
Sounds of firecrackers can be heard everywhere.
鞭 炮 聲 囧 起
In the following ten years,
在 往 後 的 十 年 中
little league baseball
少 棒 運 動
became the nation's hottest leisure activity.
成 為 全 國 最 熟 門 的 休 閒 和 運 動
Through the televised games every August,
配 合 後 來 每 年 八 月 的 電 視 轉 播
the country participated in the event with fervor.
全 國 上 下 更 是 跟 著 起 舞
Baseball players became idols to young kids
棒 球 國 手 成 了 青 少 年 的 偶 像
and heroes to the Taiwanese people.
也 是 台 灣 人 心 目 中 的 民 族 莢 雁
In later diplomatic difficulties,
在 往 後 的 外 交 困 境 中
it consoled the people of Taiwan
安 慶 了 台 灣 人
for their frustrated national pride.
不 斷 被 接 折 的 民 族 情 緒
After the winning team received flowers from
這 支 勝 利 的 隊 伍
the students of Chongshan Girls High School,
在 接 受 中 山 女 中 學 生 的 獻 花 後
they boarded army jeeps
登 上 禮 車
for a parade around the city
遊 行 市 區
filled with cheering crowds.
接 受 民 眾 的 歡 呼
International situations in the 1970s
1970 年 代 以 後 的 國 際 局 勢
took a great turn.
發 生 重 大 變 化
Taiwan was about to face
台 灣 即 將 開 始 遭 遇
a series of diplomatic failures.
一 連 串 驚 濤 駭 浪 般 的 外 交 挫 敗
With the change in
隨 著 中 華 民 國
Taiwan's international position,
在 國 際 地 位 上 的 改 變
the history of the Taiwanese people
台 灣 人 民 的 歷 史
underwent a theatrical development.
又 有 了 非 常 戲 劇 性 的 發 展
Taiwan began to look for
台 灣
its position
將 在 國 際 政 治 現 實 的 考 驗 下
under the realities of international politics,
開 始 尋 找 自 己 的 定 位
and continued to advance in a hard environment.
繼 續 在 嚴 苗 的 環 境 中 奮 力 前 進